Guide to the Sanford J. Rosen Legal Files on Alger Hiss TAM.736
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sanford J. Rosen Legal Files on Alger Hiss
1970-1978, 1981, 1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rosen, Sanford J. (Sanford Jay Rosen)
TAM.736
1.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 half manuscript box.
17.37 Gigabytes
Sanford Jay Rosen is a founding and senior partner at Rosen Bien Galvan & Grunfeld LLP in San Francisco, California, where he concentrates his practice on constitutional and civil rights law, employment law, consumer law, complex commercial litigation, and litigation involving attorneys. He was working for the American Civil Liberties Union during the time he was Alger Hiss' attorney in the 1972 Hiss et al. v. Hampton et al. case. The plaintiffs' annuity applications were denied due to certain provisions of the "Hiss Act." Rosen's papers relate to his time as Alger Hiss' lawyer during this 1972 case to restore his federal pension. Materials include drafts and research for memos, correspondence, and legal research, as well as files related to Alger Hiss' friendship with Mr. Rosen.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sanford Jay Rosen, September 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.002.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Sanford Jay Rosen is a founding and senior partner at Rosen Bien Galvan & Grunfeld LLP in San Francisco, California, where he concentrates his practice on constitutional and civil rights law, employment law, consumer law, complex commercial litigation, and litigation involving attorneys. He was working for the American Civil Liberties Union during the time he was Alger Hiss' attorney in the 1972 Hiss et al. v. Hampton et al. case.
Content Description
Sanford Jay Rosen's papers relate to his time as Alger Hiss' lawyer during a case to restore his federal pension. Materials include drafts and research for memos, correspondence, and legal research from the Hiss et al. v. Hampton et al. case, as well as files related to Alger Hiss' friendship with Mr. Rosen.
Former employees of the federal government, plaintiffs in the Hiss v. Hampton case had applied for annuities under the Civil Service Retirement Act. Their applications were denied by the Civil Service Commission due to certain provisions of the "Hiss Act." In the Hiss v. Hampton case, Sanford J. Rosen won a dispositive summary judgment motion that declared the Hiss Act an unconstitutional ex post facto law.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Actions and defenses (Administrative law); Espionage, Soviet -- United States.; Legal documents.; Espionage, American -- History -- 20th century.; United States -- Officials and employees -- Pensions.; United States -- Hiss Act; Hiss, Alger; Rosen, Sanford J. (Sanford Jay Rosen); Communist Party of the United States of America; Strasburger, Richard
- Draft of Major Memo, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Major Memo Research, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Jurisdiction, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Property, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Freeman v. U.S., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bill of Attainder, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Oral Argument, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- News Clips, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Strasburger Legislative History, Hiss-Strasburger Memo Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hiss-Strasburger, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hiss - Miscellaneous Research, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Civil Service Proceedings, Hiss Papers, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Notes and Research, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, Hiss #2, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hiss, Alger Additional Correspondence #3, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Hiss Correspondence #4, 1973-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Hiss Case Correspondence, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Hiss et al. v. Hampton et al. Vol. 1, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Hiss et al. v. Hampton et al. Vol. 2, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)